"Previously on The Mentalist"
Lisbon, I just want you to know
I'm okay.
"And I'm gonna miss you."
- Patrick.
- Kim.
Thank you for this.
I needed the company.
I'm here to make you
an offer.
The Bureau is willing to drop
all of the charges against you
if you come
and work for us.
"You are on U.S. soil now."
This is the deal.
- Take it or leave it.
- I leave it.
They conceded
to all your demands.
Every single one.
How did you do it?
Well, remember that thumb drive
we found in Bertram's wine cellar?
The encrypted database.
"It's a list of Blake Association members.
I used it as leverage."
- But we never broke the encryption.
- Yeah, F.B.I. doesn't know that.
Got a desk ready for you.
You can work right back here.
Eh, I don't need a desk.
- Really? You work standing up?
- Lying down.
- I need a couch.
- Really?
Really. Opens the mind.
That's why shrinks have you lie down.
I wouldn't know.
You can't have a sofa here.
- You've never been to a shrink?
- No.
Interesting. That's a lie.
We'll come back to that.
Why? Why can't I have a couch?
Only grade 3 employees and above
can have sofas.
Sofas, couches, potatoes, "potatoes."
- Uh, what grade am I?
- You're a consultant.
You're not in the grading system.
- What grade are you?
- Four.
You can apply for an ergonomic
chair if you have back issues
but you'll have to get
a doctor's note.
No. I asked for a couch,
and Abbott, your boss
said I could have a couch.
You can have a sofa.
You just can't have it here.
No couch, no me.
Okay, you don't understand
the deal here.
You don't get to make the rules.
Yes, I do,
and you've already seen that I do.
Why do you say that you've
never been to a shrink?
What are you ashamed of?
I'm sorry
that I deceived you, Patrick.
- Truly. Good.
- But you didn't deceive me.
I'm glad you feel that way.
I didn't intend to get so involved.
I was meant to confirm your identity
and keep tabs on you.
And then we started talking,
and I...
Whatever. I'm sorry.
And I will attempt
to make it up to you
by being as honest
as possible in the future.
Do you always mask your guilt
with anger?
There's nothing in my life
that I'm ashamed of.
But it is my life
and whether I have been
to a shrink or I haven't
that's not your business.
Uh, this is the conference
room, obviously.
The break room is through here.
What did you see
a shrink about?
Okay.
- I will get you a couch.
- Hmm. Good.
I like the club style,
but obviously bigger.
Worn leather, something I can
really snuggle into, you know?
Just like the one I had
at the CBI.
Fischer. Saddle up.
We're going to Corpus Christi.
Five DEA agents were murdered.
- Five?
- Five. Let's go.
There's three different
caliber casings
so there were three shooters,
maybe more.
These people never knew
what hit 'em.
Well, they found
the security camera.
It was hidden in the clock.
Got another one here
hidden in a lamp.
They knew what they were
looking for.
One of the agents survived
the initial shooting.
See the streaks of blood?
He was trying to crawl to safety
when he was killed.
Clean job.
No witnesses, no footage.
Why is there a mirror
in this room
and why is it set so high
on the wall?
- Another camera.
- Et voilà.
Listen. I know who did this.
I know it.
What agent Higgins means
is the DEA has strong reason
to believe a Corpus Christi
narcotics organization
is behind the murders,
the Gulf Coast Ring.
- Why would they want to do this?
- Retaliation.
Last month, we took
100 kilos off the ring
and shot and killed
one of their lieutenants.
We've been hearing
they wanted payback.
I.A. investigated.
It was a clean shooting.
We first caught wind
of the ring two years ago.
They're disciplined,
they're organized
and highly secretive.
The bust we made
a few weeks ago
was the first dent we made
in their operations.
But they still control virtually
all drug flow into Corpus Christi.
Where were you
when the shootings occurred?
Was home.
I was on surveillance late
the night before.
Who runs the Gulf Coast Ring?
We don't know.
But we do have a profile.
We think this Mr. X is an intelligent
and disciplined businessman
mostly likely using
a legitimate front as cover.
- Hiding in plain sight.
- That's right.
Look, most of these guys
they want you to know
who they are.
It drives them.
But this one
it's like he doesn't have an ego.
- Well, that's odd, isn't it?
- What's that?
Well, well you said that Mr. X
is disciplined.
Uh, I would think that
shooting five DEA agents
is anything but disciplined.
Who do you have in mind?
There's a few possibilities.
Hector Ruiz.
A real estate developer
based in Corpus Christi.
But he has dealings
throughout Texas.
Francisco Perez,
a.k.a. Paco
a Colombian national
with ties to a drug cartel.
Now we know
he's in the city now
but we're still not sure why.
He's only been in the states
a few months.
Michael Ellis.
He runs a financial group.
It's mostly private equity,
but some international business.
He's been investigated
for tax fraud
SEC violations.
But nothing's stuck.
- Um, who? Who? who's this?
- It's Richie Vargas.
He's the ring member
who got killed in the bust.
- Yeah, no, the woman.
- Oh.
It's Krystal Markham,
Vargas' girlfriend.
Hm. You know where we can
find her?
Uh, we've questioned her in the past.
Few times.
She wasn't much help.
Do you know where
we can find her?
"Shut that door!"
"Wylie, you get anything from
the DEA footage we sent you?"
As a matter of fact, yes.
- IDs on all three gunmen.
- That was fast.
Uh, Once I pulled clean photos
from the footage
it was just a matter of running
a facial recognition program.
All three were
in the federal database.
- Well, who are they?
- According to Corpus Christi P.D.
they're local street criminals.
Nothing to do
with the Gulf Coast Ring.
Maybe the DEA was wrong.
Or maybe the ring
freelanced out the shooting.
Addresses are current,
but they're not gonna help.
Local police checked them out.
Gunmen are long gone.
So we have to wait for a hit
on the BOLO. I hate that.
You wanna take a drive
down to Corpus Christi?
Yeah, let's go.
Did you listen to the audio
on the DEA surveillance video?
Yeah. Why?
Well, you couldn't see the gunmen's car
but you could hear its engine.
So?
So maybe we can use that.
That's a fantastic idea.
Every engine model has its own
unique audio signature.
If we can analyze the gunmen's
and compare it to known
engine signatures
we might just have a match.
- Great. Call me if you get something.
- You got it.
- He can do it?
- Yeah.
- F.B.I.
"He's there right now?"
Krystal Markham?
- Yes?
- Agent Fischer with the F.B.I.
this is Patrick Jane.
We'd like to ask you a few questions
about recent shooting at a DEA office.
I don't know anything about it.
Five DEA agents
lost their lives, ma'am.
Oh, yes. I remember now.
It was on the news. Terrible.
- What about it?
- Well, some people think
the Gulf Coast Ring did it.
revenge for the death of your boyfriend
Richie Vargas.
- Richie wasn't my boyfriend.
- No? Uh, what would you call him?
A friend. A good friend.
And I'm very sad that he is gone.
- Um, he was a sweet guy.
- He was a gangster.
- I didn't know that.
- No?
I never asked him
what he did for a living.
That can be a rude
question, you know?
Excuse me.
- May I go?
- Uh, yeah. Of, of course.
Um, but first, could I...
Could I get your phone number?
I told you
I don't know anything.
I believe you.
That's not why I'm asking
for your number.
I'm a little out of practice.
I'm sorry.
It's been a while.
- Oh. You want my number?
- Yes
then I could possibly call it
and maybe we could...
Wow. I don't know.
I never, um...
Uh, that was Wylie
back at the office.
He'd ID'd the gunmen's vehicle.
Late '60s Chevy Impala.
There are three in the area
but none of them's registered
to the gunmen.
Do we know
where the three are?
One of them's in downtown
Corpus Christi.
Second was spotted near
the warehouse district
and the third is in Bella Vista,
so we have our day cut out for us.
Thanks for your time,
Miss Markham.
Could you give us a moment?
- Yeah.
- Thank you.
So you, you were, you were saying
you've never...
I never dated a cop.
Well, nor will you now.
I'm not a cop.
- Well, what are you then?
- I'm not a what, I'm a who.
And I'd be happy to tell you
which who over dinner.
Thank you. I'll call you.
Maybe I'll answer.
- Did you just ask her out?
- Yep.
Good for you, I guess.
- I'm surprised.
- Hm?
I wouldn't have thought
that she was your type.
She thinks the Impala
we're looking for
is in the warehouse district.
- She does? How can you tell?
- I can tell.
Oh. Oh, you think...
You think she knows more
than she's saying.
That's, that's why
you asked her out.
No. I asked her out 'cause
she's just my type.
- She say yes?
- She did.
Huh. Huh.
She may be your type
but you don't seem like hers.
Nah, she was happy
I asked her.
Once I convinced her
I wasn't a cop.
Are we gonna go anywhere?
"Hey, Cho. Fischer thinks the gunmen
are holed up in the marina warehouse."
"I'm texting you the address now."
- This our car?
- Yep.
Okay, you two take the side
and the rear of the warehouse.
You're with us.
Krystal, it's Patrick Jane.
Give me a call
when you get a chance.
I wanna know if you wanna meet me
for dinner tonight.
Clear.
- Clear.
- Let's check the back.
"Clear."
"Clear on the side."
Clear.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
Think we got something.
"I'm coming in."
Found the gunmen.
Ooh.
Hey, Krystal.
No, no. Now's a good time.
So how about dinner tonight?
Great. Great.
Let's say 8:00. Um...
Shall I pick you up, or...
or meet you there?
Awesome. Look forward to it.
So all three victims
were killed in the same fashion.
Their throats were slit first.
That accounts
for the amount of blood.
And then for good measure,
I suppose
they were re-shot in the head.
Close range.
Someone sure wanted
these men dead.
You work any cartel
murders before?
Enough to know this fits
their MO.
- Just what I was thinking.
- Got it.
Gunmen dead, justice served.
Are we gonna be here
much longer?
'Cause I got some plans.
Here we go.
Got a burner phone.
- No numbers in the contacts.
- Call log?
Six calls made,
all in the past three days
- all to the same number.
- Try it.
Disconnected.
The phone company says the number
was disconnected yesterday.
Who was it registered to?
Frank Price, which just so happens
to be a known alias of...
Francisco "Paco" Perez.
34, Colombian national.
And has strong family ties
to the Espedes cartel in Bogotá.
You said he's been in the states
the last three months.
- Doing what?
- I'm not sure.
- Before that?
- Again, not sure.
Colombian records aren't
what they could be.
- And you like him for our Mr. X?
- Yeah. Always have.
The other suspects,
Ruiz and Ellis?
They fit the profile,
but, uh, I've met 'em
talked to 'em.
Running a drug ring? Murder?
I don't see them
as being capable.
Then why not just move in
on Perez?
He was a hard sell
to my supervisors.
Our intel tells us that Perez
is a middleman
between the cartel
and the Corpus Christi drug ring
not the man in charge.
But for my money
He's the guy.
We're having a hard time
tracking Perez down.
What else can you
tell us about him?
Not much.
Perez keeps a low profile.
To be honest, I'm surprised
he left behind a burner cell.
It's not like him.
It's sloppy.
Thank you.
Sure. Thanks.
Are you gonna tell me
who you are?
Oh, no, that was just
a sales pitch.
I never, uh, really tell anyone
who I actually am.
That's why we're
so well-matched.
I think you're the same.
- You think?
- Well, uh...
there's a real Krystal
that you don't let anybody see.
Underneath the glamour
and the smiles, uh
there's someone that's honest
and strong and down to earth.
Maybe.
Well, that's the Krystal
I wanna meet.
You throw a pretty good line
for a guy who's out of practice.
I'm doing all right, am I? Excellent.
So what's with
the wedding ring?
Oh, um...
That's a long story.
Maybe we should order
some drinks.
Good idea.
Excuse me.
- Hey.
Come.
- Great minds.
- Right.
So how's it going with Jane
and the girlfriend?
Oh, it's a dead end,
if you ask me
but Jane certainly seems
to be enjoying himself.
He usually does.
Hello. From the gentlemen
at the bar.
- Oh.
- Oh, boy.
Oh, those gentlemen?
Oh, great. They're coming.
Okay. Oh.
Hello, ladies.
I'm Dale. This is Mike.
Hi.
- I'm Kim.
- I'm Teresa.
- Teresa. Beautiful name.
- Thank you.
Are you two in town for
the orthodontics conference?
- Oh. Uh, no.
- No. No. We're... we're cops.
You're kidding.
No, uh, actually, we're FBI.
Oh.
Cool.
Well, it was nice to meet you.
- Have a nice night.
- Hm.
- Thank you.
- Never fails.
Dale. Oh.
That reminds me.
- What is it?
- It's your badge.
District sent it to me today.
Congratulations.
- You look surprised.
- No. I...
Yeah, I just... I guess
it didn't feel real.
Now it's... It's real.
- I'm in the F.B.I.
- Welcome.
Thank you.
Oh, my God.
Oh, my God, that's the craziest
story I've ever heard.
- You killed him?
- Mm.
That explains why you still
wear your wedding ring.
Hm. I guess.
You poor man.
What you've been through?
I can't imagine.
Well, you've been through
some tough times yourself.
Mm, nah, nothing like that.
I don't buy the tough girl act.
I think...
you cared about Vargas a lot
and it hurt you deeply
when he was killed.
Sure, it hurt.
Well, loss has its way
of paralyzing you. It...
It stops you from moving on
in your life
and as hard as that is
and as guilty as you feel, it's...
That's what you have to do.
Move on.
That's what
I'm trying to do, anyhow.
Trying.
And this investigation
of yours.
- Is it important?
- Yes.
- To you, I mean?
Maybe I can help.
I thought you didn't know anything.
"You lied to us, Miss Markham."
I didn't want to withhold information
but you have to understand,
I can't get involved in all this.
- And now you can?
- Well, what can I say?
Someone changed my mind.
What can you tell us
about Paco Perez?
He has a condo that he uses
by the beach.
Uh, Richie and I went there
to party a couple times.
- Do you know the address?
Oh, yeah, uh
2014 Ocean something.
It's, it's right on the water.
Is there anything else
you can tell us about Perez?
Just that he'd probably kill me
if he knew I was talking to you.
Has he threatened you before?
No. But he's a violent man.
Are you sure that this is safe?
That I'm safe?
You have nothing to worry
about, Miss Markham.
No one outside this room will ever
find out you cooperated with us.
Trust me.
- Any luck?
- Perez was definitely living here
but no sign of him
when we arrived.
You think he knew
we were coming?
Uh, it's hard to say, but it looks
like he left in a hurry.
TV was still on.
The condo building
has security cameras.
See if you can pull the footage.
We might able to see what car
he was driving
or if he left with anyone.
- We're on it.
- All right.
All right.
Phones, computers
any sig intel we can use
to trace Perez.
I want all of it.
And he has a head start
so let's move.
Clock's ticking.
- Thanks again for the ride.
- Oh, it's my pleasure.
Can I walk you in?
Uh, if you walk me in,
I might invite you in
and we both know
where that would lead.
- Oh, you're trouble.
- Harmless as a fly.
That makes me the spider.
I don't know how I feel about that.
Right at home, I imagine.
- Next time. Okay?
- So there's a next time?
If you want,
and if you call me.
You know what I mean.
Tomorrow. I'll call you tomorrow.
Good.
- Bye.
"Where have you been?"
What are you doing here, Paco?
I had nowhere else to go.
The FBI just raided my place.
Okay, that doesn't
answer my question.
Why are you here
in my house?
I think you know why I am here.
I think you sent the FBI
to my condo.
I think you wanted them
to find me and to arrest me.
I don't know what you're
talking about.
Enough!
You know who I work for.
You know what they would do
when they find out
that you ratted me out
to the feds.
And you know what I would do.
Don't you ever threaten me,
you little bitch.
Did you forget
who you're talking to?
I run this town. I'm the boss.
Show some respect.
Now.
Let's start over.
Why would I talk
to the FBI?
Don't, don't, don't play dumb!
With me out of the way,
you have a straight line
to the Espedes cartel.
But you just can't take me out.
Otherwise, Colombia? Gone.
Your product? Gone.
You? Gone.
So this little game you are playing with
the FBI, it's not gonna work.
Yes, it is.
Five DEA agents are dead
and the FBI thinks
that you killed them.
I mean, I may not be able
to touch you
but what if I made it look
like someone else did?
Oh, you never thought of that?
Relax. Paco.
Uh, if I wanted to kill you...
You'd be dead.
Don't worry.
I'm not gonna kill you.
Not now, anyway.
"I thought you were gonna
call me tomorrow."
It's tomorrow somewhere.
Bali, I think.
It's a problem?
No. No problem.
I'm just surprised.
It happens so rarely these days.
"I'm calling because I wanna
see you tomorrow."
"You're free?"
Mm. I have some errands to run
and some things to take care of
but I should be free
in the evening.
It's a date.
- Good night, Patrick.
- Good night, Krystal.
We have a BOLO out on Perez.
Corpus Christi PD's gonna
help with the search.
What's this?
Security camera footage
from Perez's apartment building.
- You got anything?
- Not yet.
The camera only catches
the front of the building
so Perez could have
come and gone
without us even knowing about it.
Ladies, quick question. Huh?
Which shirt do I wear?
Jane, we're kinda in the middle
of something right now.
Please, I need the help.
It'll only take a second.
Huh? Which one?
Uh this or this?
- Are you sure?
- It's... Fine, that one.
Eh.
Jane, really? Come on.
We're trying to track down Perez.
Are you gonna actually help with
this investigation, or what?
Well, who says I'm not?
Oh, you're helping
by going on a date.
Well, it paid off once, didn't it?
By the way, thank you
very much for the couch.
Warms the place up tremendously.
He is up to something
with that woman.
- Yeah, I'll say.
- No. I mean he knows something
that he's not telling us.
I've seen it a thousand times.
I don't know. He seemed
pretty interested in her.
- She's not even his type.
- That's what I said.
- What is his type?
- I don't know.
Uh, this is a dead end.
Uh, maybe Perez knew
about the cameras.
- It was worth a try.
- You're right.
At the DEA's office,
the gunmen knew
about two of the hidden
security cameras.
- Right.
- But not the third. Why?
- Bad intel?
- Maybe, but even so
where did the intel come from?
How did they find out about
the two hidden security cameras
- in the first place?
- I don't know.
But I do know
where we can find out.
Hello, Patrick.
Hi. Uh, just wanted to make sure
we're still on for tonight.
Mm, I'm looking forward to it.
Uh, do you want to come
by the house?
Love to. What time?
- Let's say 7:00.
- I'll see you then.
Bye.
Comfy?
Don't worry.
It'll be a short ride.
So who knew about
the hidden cameras?
Me.
- My colleagues.
- And the gunmen.
Somebody told them. Who?
Maybe someone from
the cleaning crews.
One of the techs
that installed the cameras.
Drug ring could have bought off
any number of people.
Look, what I do know is that
no one on my team would do this.
Pull up a seat.
It's gonna take a while to download.
You should have thought
things through, Paco.
You should have been smarter.
Ah, but then, you are a man.
"Corpus Christi police department.
How can I help you?"
Yes. I think I saw
the man on the news
that you're looking for,
Paco Perez?
"Where did you see him?"
Uh, heading into an empty
house in my neighborhood.
I thought it was strange because the
house has been empty for months.
"What's the address, ma'am?"
945 Clinton Street.
"I have officers responding."
"If you see him, do not
approach him on your own."
- "Understand?"
- Yes, of course.
"What's your name?"
Sorry to have to run.
I will kill you.
You hear me, bitch?
I'll kill you!
Goodbye, Paco.
You know what to do. Just...
Text me when you're done.
Down. Down, down,
down, down!
Cease fire. Cease fire.
Cease fire.
- Jackson, Salazar, with me.
- Cover!
What's up, Cho?
- We found Perez. He's dead.
- What happened?
Well, it looks like he opened
fire on Corpus Christi PD.
The officers fired back.
They had more guns.
Well, did we get anything
from the scene?
A revolver.
All six rounds were fired.
But there's something strange.
I found a bullet hole in one of
the window frames of the house.
- So?
- Well, it was at the back of the house
which means someone
was shooting from the backyard.
- I don't think Perez was alone.
- Thanks.
- Is that...
- Krystal Markham.
Higgins had said his colleagues
had interviewed her
but that's not what
interested me.
Watch this.
She's looking into the camera,
like she knew it was there.
I think she did.
These are beautiful.
Thank you.
- It's a little old-fashioned.
- I love them.
Go take a seat.
- I'll put these in water.
- Okay.
- Hi.
- "Krystal..."
I am right
in the middle of something.
Call me back a little later.
Krystal Markham
is the ringleader. Jane?
Damn, he hung up.
I thought we could have
a drink down by the water.
My friend has a boat
he lets me use.
- What do you say?
- Sounds wonderful.
All right.
Your friend lets you borrow this?
Mm-hmm. He doesn't get a chance
to use it very much anymore.
- Isn't he generous?
- Wow, some friend.
Should I be jealous?
Always.
Thank you.
How's your investigation coming?
Oh, we've had some breakthroughs.
We found Paco Perez,
thanks to you.
Oh? Is he in custody?
No, uh, dead.
Corpus Christi police
shot him dead.
Well, at least that's what
they think happened.
And you?
Oh, I like to keep an open mind.
I like that about you.
- Cheers.
Now that Paco is dead
I imagine you'll be heading
back to Austin.
In due time.
- What's keeping you here?
- You are.
Sorry.
Excuse me.
So rude.
You're a wanted man.
Maybe I'm the one
who should be jealous.
It's just work.
Nothing important.
Well, personally, I hope your
investigation drags on for weeks.
And why is that?
You and I are getting
to know each other.
Well, sadly, I don't think
it's gonna go on much longer.
I have a new theory.
- Can you share it with me?
- Sure. I trust you.
First thing that stuck out to me
was that the gunmen
knew of two of the hidden
cameras, but not a third.
Didn't make sense.
Unless, of course, the person
that sent the gunmen in
wanted them to be caught.
- Clever.
- Yeah, it is.
- And the second thing?
- Well, it's just a theory, like I said
but this Mr. X that the DEA
keeps talking about.
We know he's disciplined,
he's organized, he's careful.
- And smart.
- But?
But here's a man that runs
this huge drug ring.
And doesn't just run it.
He runs it seamlessly.
And yet no one knows
who he is.
He's a man that's completely
void of ego.
And in all my life,
I don't know that I've ever met a man
who could do that.
A man who would completely
shun all attention?
That just got me thinking, and...
Well, you know, maybe this Mr. X
is a woman.
- That's quite an interesting theory.
- Yeah, I think so.
I'm not loving this.
I think I'm gonna open
another bottle.
Oh.
I like it.
I'm curious about something.
And, and don't worry
if you can't answer this.
I won't.
This woman.
Who do you think she is?
You.
- Well, what makes you say that?
- You're smart.
Smart enough to let people
think that you're not.
Which is exactly the trait
that allowed Mr. X to be
a mystery for all these years.
Besides, I knew better
than to think
that you were interested
in me, because
well, you were interested in me.
- You underestimate yourself.
- Not this time.
Well, I guess we'll never know.
Hm.
A question. If I...
If I am so capable,
So smart, as you say
how did I end up here?
Where did I go wrong?
It wasn't anything you did.
You were flawless. Really.
And the way you set
the gunmen up to be caught
and killing them, and linking
the murder to Perez
and having Perez killed the way you did,
my particular favorite.
I mean, the Corpus Christi police
probably still think that they shot him.
You're wrong about
one thing, Patrick.
I didn't have Paco killed.
I shot him myself.
My mistake.
Yes, it is.
If you shoot me,
you'll be caught.
Look around, Patrick.
No witnesses.
No.
But...
the FBI...
has been listening
to everything you've said.
And they will be arriving...
right about...
Now.
Nice try.
This is the F.B.I.
Drop your weapon now.
Bye.
- Jane? You okay?
- Oh, I'm fine. Barely.
You guys took your time
getting here, didn't you?
Another minute,
I would have been...
bobbing around there
in the marina like a, a dead duck.
- Maybe you'll learn your lesson.
- Wh..., what lesson is that?
If you'd actually told us about
your plan in advance
we'd have had time to get here.
I've been trying to tell him
that for years.
Oh, Cho, you're with me,
aren't you?
No, I'm with them.
You're a terrible communicator.
You're just lucky we found
the right boat.
Okay, well, yeah
maybe I need to work
on my communication skills.
But, you know, no problem.
Thanks for solving the crime
and just a little hypothermia.
I'll get over it.
Whew!